<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thinklens</title>
    <link>http://thinklens.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Thinklens</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://thinklens.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Terrain of Points and Opinions</title>
      <link>http://thinklens.com/the-terrain-of-points-and-opinions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://thinklens.com/the-terrain-of-points-and-opinions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I hear an opinion being discussed with passion, the speaker is usually presenting a lopsided view of the situation. Something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/01.png&#34; alt=&#34;lopsided&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s not made clear by the speaker is the thing which makes their point real in the eyes of their listeners is the subtle, emotional points they&amp;rsquo;re making in support of it, which, if examined with diligent effort, would make the situation look more like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/02.png&#34; alt=&#34;points supporting a larger point&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you take the effort to make a few counter points on your own, taking the time to flesh out a story about why someone might hold a counter belief, the situation can gradually start to look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/03.png&#34; alt=&#34;things balance out&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, if you reevaluate the situation, taking care to consider how you truly feel about each side and where you stand regardless of other people&amp;rsquo;s opinions, you might find yourself feeling the most comfortable somewhere in the middle, not fully committed to either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/04.png&#34; alt=&#34;life is not made up of facts&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point in your examination, you might start to get an eerie feeling that perhaps the terrain you&amp;rsquo;re now exploring is much bigger and more malleable than you originally thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dichotomous view that the speaker presented at the start can start to look like an effect of a particular vantage point &amp;mdash; instead of being based solely on facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you could decide to take the courageous step to look at things from an entirely different vantage point, which could cause the terrain to shift and expand again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/05.png&#34; alt=&#34;so many ways of seeing&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This constant shifting can start to feel a little overwhelming. You can start to feel a little lost and confused, which, in the realm of thought and idea, is a particularly unsettling feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you&amp;rsquo;ll even get caught up in a temporary loop of doubts, thinking for a moment that perhaps nothing in the realm of the mind is solid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after some time, you will probably come to the idea that what you are doing is completely sane and logical. Who, in their right mind, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want to fully explore the terrain of their mind and the options they have to pick from before starting down the rode of choosing one opinion over another?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you call this to mind, it can be easier to see that what usually makes an opinion seem real or true is the emotional force that you associate with its subtler points. For example, if you were exploring your thoughts about some activity, say soccer or baseball, you might think back to the last time you played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you let go of your attachments to certain views and emotions, however, and take a little time to consider all of the people, ideas, and feelings influencing you, the terrain around this particular issue can start to loosen up and feel more like an interconnected web&amp;hellip; and less like a seesaw leaning more one way than another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/06.png&#34; alt=&#34;a web&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feeling of interconnectedness is beautiful. It can be a beautiful experience to stop and watch yourself as you feel around inside of it, looking for where you feel like you fit among all of the various points and opinions and those of everyone you know. You can see and feel how your opinions about things shift with attention and change texture depending on where you go and explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gradually, as things loosen up and you learn to treat your opinions as just opinions (instead of assuming they&amp;rsquo;re hard and solid like perhaps you were doing before), you can almost feel the significance of some of your larger opinions shrinking, as if giving less credence to smaller opinions weakens the power that all opinions have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/07.png&#34; alt=&#34;as equals&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting place because you can really start to see how there&amp;rsquo;s much less at stake here than you once thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can sometimes feel like your whole life or identity is at stake in certain conversations, but allowing yourself the freedom to move in and out of the flow can feel like learning how to swim on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you start swimming, it might feel like you&amp;rsquo;ll have to swim forever, never finding solid ground&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feeling of swimming can give you an appreciation for why it feels so clean and safe to speak in terms of dichotomies, as if the act of opining a division in the realm of ideas automatically creates some solid ground to stand on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the more you swim, the more this world opens up to you. And fear is replaced by a desire to trace back to the foundations of every opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/08.png&#34; alt=&#34;the ocean&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process of learning about the terrain of a conversation is more of an intuitive process than one that can be conducted on a purely logical level. It can leave you feeling emotionally shaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, especially if you&amp;rsquo;ve rushed through all of this, things can start to feel pretty congested, like there&amp;rsquo;s nowhere you can go to get a better view of how things fit together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can feel like everything, every thought, every opinion, is a burden you have to carry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can even feel like you sometimes lose track of where you stand altogether. Sometimes, when I get into a spot like this, I want to scream and yell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gradually, though, your thoughts will slow down and you&amp;rsquo;ll start to refocus on the world around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone is still here and this has all only been a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/09.png&#34; alt=&#34;people&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things get confusing because everyone involved isn&amp;rsquo;t just bringing themselves into the conversation, but, also, the terrain of their opinions, including everyone they know and everything they think they know is significant to everyone they know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And everyone has their own experiences, memories, relationships, and ideas to navigate, just like you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each person who takes part in a discussion represents more than just the person standing there. They&amp;rsquo;re a wealth of experience and emotion, always growing, always learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each individual is a multitude. A multitude among multitudes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/10.png&#34; alt=&#34;combined experience&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the network we create is not our own, but set against a backdrop of ever-expanding, ever-evolving networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that we will one day arrive at an opinion that represents some kind of final truth is an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, when you trace things back far enough, there are no answers. Everyone is equal in this respect, in the realm of thought. I could claim that what really matters is the connections, the network, the metaphorical reality we create with our relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this would be disingenuous, as all I can say with complete honesty is that I like traveling through it all and seeing the tides rise and the landscape shift. As if the world wasn&amp;rsquo;t destined to make sense for us at all&amp;hellip; but it sometimes gives us a glimpse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/points/11.png&#34; alt=&#34;the world&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Are Thoughts?</title>
      <link>http://thinklens.com/what-are-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://thinklens.com/what-are-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I think thoughts matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/00.png&#34; alt=&#34;thoughts matter&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can go for days inside my thoughts, with only little breaks in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little like building sand castles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/01.png&#34; alt=&#34;sand castle&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I come back to reality things can be pretty disappointing. I’m no longer married to the girl sitting across from me on the train. I didn’t write a poem that made everyone in the room cry. I forgot to stand up for myself when it counted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/02.png&#34; alt=&#34;where was i?&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to think that thoughts were the secret to everything. I would think: &amp;ldquo;If I can change my thoughts, I can change who I am. I can become anyone I want to be.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/03.png&#34; alt=&#34;become anyone&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, I think of thoughts more like water flowing through a landscape. Have you ever seen water travel on a flat surface like a driveway? It usually keeps going along one primary path over and over again, sometimes taking a detour that eventually meets resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/04.png&#34; alt=&#34;water detour&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts are kind of like this. They usually travel along the same pathways over and over again, one thought leading to another, until major resistance is met. Then, however, they find a way around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/05.png&#34; alt=&#34;thought leads to thought&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I try to pay attention to each thought as it comes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever listened closely to the tone of voice that a thought speaks in? Or, if you’re a visual thinker, the mood and character expressing an image or vision? Usually the voice or character will be one you identify as your own, but sometimes there’s a hint of someone else who influenced you at some point in your life. For example, an authoritative or reprimanding voice could sound like one of your parents or a school teacher, and a childlike voice could remind you of your own voice as a child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/06.png&#34; alt=&#34;voices&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the impression that it’s not often that someone will incorporate someone else’s voice or character into their own on purpose. Except, perhaps, when you’re an actor or an author, in which case it’s encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about how fluid our personalities can be makes me wonder how much they influence our thoughts. Does a personality determine the types of thoughts someone can have? Is it a determining factor in making decisions? And what is a personality, anyway?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My understanding is that a personality is not the river of thoughts and emotions that flows through your mind and body, but rather your emotional experiences and feelings about this river, as if you could stand outside of it and watch it go by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/07.png&#34; alt=&#34;see the flow&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you get this constantly changing idea of your personality, of who you are, but for the most part it stays the same because the river tends to follow the same paths, uses the same voice, and has the same character that it had before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when we want to imagine how other people are going to react to a situation, we can use our experience of their river to map out what they might say or do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/08.png&#34; alt=&#34;walk on the river&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when you’re around someone whom you know really well, it can feel like both of your emotional rivers merge into one river. When this happens I think it’s natural to not even be aware of the formation of this combined river of experience, but before you know it, you’ve become caught in a flow of perfectly natural interactions. This can even happen with someone you’ve just met, if a natural trust is built early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this kind of experience can be really exciting when the flow of a conversation keeps moving back and forth into areas and dimensions that neither person expected, using the power of the combined experience to chart new territory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/09.png&#34; alt=&#34;combined experience&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This same kind of experience can happen when you’re reading a book or watching a movie. When you’re able to give yourself over to a piece of art, it can take you back into your past, help you explore old wounds or reawaken desires and ideas you forgot you had. When an author creates a world or a person that seems real, it can become possible to travel to another dimension of experience, one in which you forget that you exist. Your complete focus is given over to the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/10.png&#34; alt=&#34;inside the book&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also experience this flow, this loss of identity and immersion into a story, when you’re alone. One minute you’ll be driving or walking along and the next thing you know, you’ve just spent the last five minutes in your head, wrapped up in a story you’re telling yourself about your life or arguing with yourself over the implications of an exchange you just had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the strangest things about this immersive experience is the feeling you get upon returning to yourself, the realization that you just suspended your connection to your identity for a bit, lost track of your bodily awareness, and forgot to pay attention to what was going on around you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a little like being under water, in that all of your senses are dulled and occupied by your thoughts (the water) and you can feel pretty disconnected from what’s going on in the real world (the shore above).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/11.png&#34; alt=&#34;under water&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes after going on one of these excursions, when you come back to your body you find yourself walking or driving faster, your body might be hunched over or tense, or you might be practicing a nervous habit. It almost feels like you literally traveled somewhere else and when you came back you realized your body was responding the whole time, expressing itself in different ways as you traveled through different thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this same kind of experience can happen when you’re caught up in any kind of story, even one being played out in real life. If you’re comfortable with your role in a given situation and you have trust in the roles of the people around you, it can feel completely natural to get wrapped up in the idea of what’s happening and not pay attention to what you’re doing or saying. It all just seems to come automatically. It helps even more if you’ve participated in these same roles hundreds or thousands of times before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/12.png&#34; alt=&#34;establish a role&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to say exactly what a role is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are the everyday roles that most of us participate in at one point or another: doctor and patient, boss and employee, parent and child, friend, and lover. For most of us these roles are pretty well-established in our consciousness. Even if someone in one of these roles stopped performing according to their normally expected behavior, we’d probably continue to think of them in the same way for a while. The way we think and feel about someone in a role tends to have some persistence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there are the roles that are more subtle, which involve how we think of ourselves, how other people react to us, and how we respond to their reactions. There are many thoughts that go unspoken, feelings that go unacknowledged, imagined actions that aren’t performed, and desires that go unfulfilled, all because we felt like it wasn’t appropriate to travel into that territory in a given setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roles can be looked at as the pathways through which our thoughts and emotions, indeed the very river of our personality, move through. This isn’t to say that we don’t have choices and options when it comes to shaping our personalities and the ways we interact; every role has many facets and each one of us is usually participating in more than one role at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/13.png&#34; alt=&#34;roles are pathways&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roles are responsible for giving us options and freedom, while at the same time shaping us into the particular people that a situation requires. Many roles aren’t very well defined, so it can sometimes feel like you’re not participating in a role at all, as if no one is giving you any signals as to what is appropriate to do next. Sometimes it can feel like this when you’re at a casual gathering with friends, where you’re just expected to be yourself, and sometimes it can feel like this when you think about the grand scheme of your life: where you’ve been, what you’ve done, and all the uncertainty around what you hope to do and who you hope to become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when your role isn’t very well defined, the pressure to do or say the right thing can be overwhelming. It can be tempting to retreat into your thoughts over and over again in an effort to discover a way out. In an effort to measure a response to something you’ve never done before, you might run through scenarios in your head over and over again and try to predict what people will do or say in response. Such a process, if it becomes a habit, can lead to a constant tension between who you are and your impulse to act. You may find yourself spending a lot of your spare time thinking about who you could be, and when you come back to reality you could be quite shocked to realize the mismatch between how you imagined yourself and where you are now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/14.png&#34; alt=&#34;feeling different than you are&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a unique power of thought, the ability to take you away from everyday reality and place you in an alternate experience of what’s happening and what’s important. You may find yourself, while reading a fictional story, responding to a character’s emotions and actions as if they were occurring in the moment, as if you could stop them from making a decision or comfort them when they’re suffering. When you’re playing a video game you can immerse your thoughts in this experience of feigned reality even more, imagining that you’re actually walking through a virtual world and melding your own personality with the personalities of the characters in the game. It can serve as both practice for real life and as an escape from real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for a personality to develop, in order for it to explore what’s possible and figure out the extent to which it can push the boundaries of the roles it occupies, it needs time to solidify as well as opportunities to experiment without judgment. Thoughts, which exist halfway between one reality and another, can provide that stepping stone. A personality is solidified as it encounters the same types of thoughts over and over again, and it is given reminders of the directions it wants to grow towards with its reactions to each thought. Without the tension between one idea of reality and another idea of reality, it’s possible that there would be very little motivation to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/15.png&#34; alt=&#34;imagining a new door&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts also have the power to provide us with a sense of context and a sense of reality. It’s our thoughts, fueled by our imagination, that give us a sense of place in relation to other people. We are constantly writing and revising our interpretation of the person we are, where we are in terms of our status and the strength of our relationships, and why we’re doing what we’re doing. Thoughts serve to give us balance and provide the feeling of a solid foundation among the multitude of emotions that we’re feeling in a given moment. If someone or something makes us feel like we don’t belong or that there’s something wrong with us, our emotions can betray us and destabilize the security of our thoughts. The idea that there is a greater context to our lives—one in which our friends and families love us and where we’re doing meaningful work—can work to stabilize our emotions and bring us back to ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond just giving you an idea of what’s happening in the moment, I would guess that providing a greater context to one’s life is one of the main things people use thoughts for. Simply thinking about how one feels about current events, teammates, coworkers and family members can have a reinforcing effect on our sense of identity. These can serve as the banks of the river of our consciousness. At the same time, thoughts can fill in missing pieces to our stories or gaps in our knowledge. If something about ourselves, such as a recent habit or behavior that we just picked up, is disturbing to us, we can reason through what might be causing it and see if we can do anything about it. Similarly, if someone gets upset with us for no apparent reason, we can think about what they might be going through in other situations in their life that might explain their distress, instead of reacting directly to their feelings as if they’re only related to the present situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;centered-image&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://thinklens.com/images/what-are-thoughts/16.png&#34; alt=&#34;surround yourself with love&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>