<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thinklens</title>
    <link>http://thinklens.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Thinklens</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://thinklens.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On Creation</title>
      <link>http://thinklens.com/on-creation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://thinklens.com/on-creation/</guid>
      <description>Creation requires walking out on a path not yet discovered, knowing you will never come back, not as you are.
Creation requires pushing and pulling at unseen forces that are beyond your understanding, grappling with the very things that give life meaning.
When you come back from your journey, you are different. You see the world in a new way. That is the gift, that is the creation. You, yourself, have been transformed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Who am I?&#34; A guide for dealing with difficult emotions</title>
      <link>http://thinklens.com/who-am-i-a-guide-for-dealing-with-difficult-emotions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://thinklens.com/who-am-i-a-guide-for-dealing-with-difficult-emotions/</guid>
      <description>This guide has helped me when I have trouble dealing with tough emotions like anxiety, fear, and groundlessness. I hope it can provide some comfort to you too.
Read the corresponding section if one of the following is true:
 I&amp;rsquo;m feeling stuck I&amp;rsquo;m feeling dissatisfied I&amp;rsquo;m feeling sad I&amp;rsquo;m feeling self-hate I&amp;rsquo;m feeling self-anger I&amp;rsquo;m feeling anxious about a recurring thought I&amp;rsquo;m feeling anxious about a choice I&amp;rsquo;m feeling anxious about a friendship I&amp;rsquo;m feeling anxious about a relationship I&amp;rsquo;m feeling anxious about my career path I&amp;rsquo;m feeling anxious about my identity I&amp;rsquo;m feeling attacked I&amp;rsquo;m feeling nervous about the future</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Terrain of Points and Opinions</title>
      <link>http://thinklens.com/the-terrain-of-points-and-opinions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://thinklens.com/the-terrain-of-points-and-opinions/</guid>
      <description>When I hear an opinion being discussed with passion, the speaker is usually presenting a lopsided view of the situation. Something like this:
 What&amp;rsquo;s not made clear by the speaker is the thing which makes their point real in the eyes of their listeners is the subtle, emotional points they&amp;rsquo;re making in support of it, which, if examined with diligent effort, would make the situation look more like this:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Are Thoughts?</title>
      <link>http://thinklens.com/what-are-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://thinklens.com/what-are-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I think thoughts matter.
 I can go for days inside my thoughts, with only little breaks in between.
It’s a little like building sand castles.
 When I come back to reality things can be pretty disappointing. I’m no longer married to the girl sitting across from me on the train. I didn’t write a poem that made everyone in the room cry. I forgot to stand up for myself when it counted.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>